A Guide to the Barefoot Sanders Papers, 1940s-2009
Barefoot Sanders Papers
1940s-2009
Sanders, Barefoot (1925-2008)
2009-220; 2009-295; 2009-359; 2010-009; 2010-092
23 ft., 2 in.
Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin
Barefoot Sanders, born Harold Barefoot Sanders, Jr., was a Federal Judge on the United States District Court for the Northern District of Texas from 1979-2006, nominated by Jimmy Carter. Correspondence, news clippings, printed materials, photographs, notes, campaign material, and speeches document Barefoot Sanders personal and public life.
Biographical Note
Barefoot Sanders, born Harold Barefoot Sanders, Jr., was a Federal Judge on the United States District Court for the Northern District of Texas from 1979-2006, nominated by Jimmy Carter. He is most well known for overseeing the lawsuit to desegregate the Dallas Independent School District. Sanders had a long and distinguished career serving as a congressman in the Texas legislature, as a U.S. Attorney, as an assistant deputy attorney general, as legislative counsel to President Lyndon B. Johnson, and as a Federal Judge.
Barefoot Sanders was born in 1925, attended North Dallas High School, graduating in 1942. Sanders served in the Navy during World War II (1943-1946) on a destroyer in the Pacific Theater. He underwent training at Mercer University in Georgia and Notre Dame in Indiana. Following, his time in the military, Sanders received an A.B. (1949) from the University of Texas and a J.D. (1950) from the University of Texas School of Law. While attending UT, Barefoot was elected student body president in 1947. Furthermore, Sanders was associated with many different organizations including, Phi Delta Theta, Blue Key, Phi Delta Phi, Phi Delta Kappa and the Texas Cowboys.
Following his graduation, Sanders went into practice with the Dallas law firm Clark, West, Keller, Sanders and Butler (1950-1961, 1969-1979). Sanders married Jan Scurlock in 1952 and they had four children together. He served on the Texas Legislature for three terms from 1953 to 1958. In 1960, Sanders was instrumental in helping the Kennedy-Johnson ticket win Texas. After the election, Kennedy appointed Sanders a United States attorney. During President Johnson’s terms, Sanders was Assistant Deputy Attorney General and Assistant Attorney General (1965-1967), and legislative counsel to President Johnson (1967-1968). Sander played a small part in the transfer of power from President’s Kennedy to Johnson, when he was asked to find Federal Judge Sarah Hughes to administer the oath of office to Johnson. As legislative counsel to the president, Sanders helped shepherd many Great Society initiatives through Congress, such as the Voting Rights Act. In 1968, before leaving office, President Johnson appointed Sanders as a Federal Appellate Judge for the District of Columbia Circuit. However, Johnson’s term expired before Sanders’ confirmation by the Senate and Nixon nominated George McKinnon instead. In 1969, Sanders returned to private practice in Dallas. He ran for the United States Senate in 1972, but lost to John Tower as part of the Nixon landslide. In 1978 Sanders contemplated running again, but eventually decided against it.
Sanders returned to public service, in 1979 when President Carter appointed him to the United States District Court for the Northern District of Texas. Furthermore, he served as chief judge of the court from 1989-1995. During his time on the bench, Sanders oversaw the Tasby litigation, a desegregation plan for the Dallas Independent School District that lasted for decades until it was finally settled in 2003. During the litigation he ordered the construction of magnet schools and made most busing voluntary. Sanders also supervised the restructuring of the state hospitals for the mentally ill after a civil rights reform lawsuit, R.A.J. vs. TDMHMR. The restructuring improved living conditions and the treatment of patients in Texas’ eight state psychiatric hospitals. Sanders retired in 2006 and died of natural causes September 21, 2008 at the age of eighty-three.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, news clippings, printed materials, photographs, notes, campaign material, and speeches document Barefoot Sanders personal and public life. The bulk of Sanders’ papers consist of news clippings concerning his various careers as a lawyer, Texas congressman, U.S. attorney, assistant deputy attorney general, legislative counsel to the president, and federal judge. The papers include material from Sanders’ time in the Navy and at the University of Texas. Furthermore, the papers document Sanders’ campaigns for various public offices, such as his 1972 campaign for U.S. senator as well as his deliberations about running again in 1978. The material from Sanders’ time as a federal judge consists mainly of clippings, printed material, and speeches.
Access Restrictions
Artifacts require an appointment with artifacts curator. Contact repository.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Sanders, Barefoot, 1925-2009 -- Archives.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.
Subjects (Organizations)
University of Texas at Austin.; University of Texas. School of Law.
Subjects
Judges -- United States.; Presidents--United States--Staff.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.
Places
Dallas (Tex.); United States. Navy.; Washington (D.C.)
Separated Material
Artifacts separated to Artifact Collection and require an appointment with artifacts curator. Contact repository.
Related Material
Barefoot Sanders’ other professional papers have been archived at the following institutions:
LBJ Presidential Library and Museum - all papers related to his service in the LBJ administration.
Tarlton Law Library, the University of Texas School of Law - all judicial papers from his career as a United States Federal District Judge for the Northern District of Texas.
Southern Methodist University Law Library - all judicial papers related to the Tasby case surrounding the integration of the Dallas Public Schools.
Detailed Description of the Papers
- Inventory
  - [Stored off-site at LSF]
  - North Dallas High School (Box 2009-220/1)
  - Military:
    - Mercer College and Notre Dame
    - Mercer and the Navy
    - Navy – Military, 1944
    - Diary, 1946
    - Navy – Photographs
  - University of Texas:
    - General Correspondence, 1947-1949
    - Telegrams, 1948
    - “Texas Ranger,” 1943, 1949
    - History Notes
    - Travel in Central America, 1946-1947
    - Hildebrand Moot Court Contest, 1949
    - General Papers
    - Photographs
    - Ephemera
    - Clippings
  - Dallas 1950s:
    - Attorney Barr Association work
    - Correspondence with Jan Scurlock, 1950-1951
    - Ephemera
    - Clippings
  - Texas Congress, 1952-1959:
    - Clippings
  - Kennedy Campaign:
    - Planning Campaign, 1960
  - U.S. Attorney:
    - U.S. Attorney, 1960s
    - LBJ Inauguration, 1965
  - Legislative Counsel:
    - Legislative Counsel on LBJ’s staff
  - Failed Federal Judgeship: (Box 2009-295/2)
    - Congratulatory Mail – Judgeship – Vol. One, 1968
    - Coming Back to Texas, 1969
    - Speech File – Barefoot Sanders, August 1, 1969
  - LBJ Library, 1971
  - Speech Notes
  - Speech Material
  - Speech File, January 17, 1975
  - 1972 Senate Campaign:
    - 1972 Senate Campaign Material
    - Jan Sanders’ Campaign Notes, 1971
    - Itineraries, 1972
    - Press Release Pool to Barefoot
    - Barefoot Sanders – Campaign Manual, 1971
    - Campaign Chairmen, Address Book, 1972
    - Senate Campaign Photographs, 1971-1972
    - Campaign Ephemera – bumper stickers, invitations, flyers, and envelopes, 1972
    - Ephemera, 1970s
  - Federal Judgeship:
    - Printed Materials
    - Ephemera
    - Correspondence
    - Case Material
    - Photographs
    - Clippings, Court Cases
  - Memorial:
    - Portrait unveiling, 2009
    - Memorial Service – Research by Larry Temple, Oral History Interview from LBJ Library
    - Memorial Materials, 2008-2009
    - Tribute to the Sanders, 2008-2009
  - Federal Judgeship: (Box 2009-220/3)
    - Speeches:
      - Speech notes, 1979-2005
      - U.S. Constitution
        - Speech outline, 1987
        - Notes – Material, September 1987-2005
      - Black History Month Speech, February 26, 2004
      - Info-References: Other material for speeches
      - “Complex Litigation: - State Bar Talk, March 18, 1888
      - Dallas Bar Association – Future of Business Dispute Resolution, December 8, 1997
      - Criminal Defense Lawyers Seminar – speech notes, October 1988
      - Kennedy Assassination
        - Kennedy Dedication, November 22, 1993
        - Notes regarding assassination, November 22, 1963
      - Federal Rules Amendments Speech outline, December 1, 1993
      - The Brethren: Book review info.
      - Larry Temple: Lecture “Higher Education ,”, November 1986
      - DISD Learning Centers Remarks, 1995
      - Commencement Ceremony Science/Engineering Magnet, May 12, 1995
      - DISD Townview Ribbon Cutting, August 13, 1995
      - Federal Bar Association – Installation and Update Remarks, June 1995
    - Honors, articles, reunions:
      - Honors:
        - Barefoot Sanders Endowed Presidential Scholarship, UT, 1994
        - Martin Luther King Justice Award, 2006
        - University of Texas Justice Award, November 3, 2005
        - SMU Reception, January 12, 2005
        - SMU Degree of Doctor of Law, honoris causa, May 16, 1999
        - Hispanic Bar Association Award, 2007 (Box 2009-220/4)
        - DISD Luncheon, Magnet School Award, October 30, 2003
        - CASA Dinner, etc.
        - Dallas Bar Association Professionalism Award, 2002
        - Texas Bar Foundation, Outstanding 50-year lawyers, 2002
      - Articles:
        - Legal Legends, 2000
        - American Bar Association Litigation Article (Portia and Barry McNeil)
        - Westward Portrait article
        - Dallas City Herald, June 1, 1986
        - High profile, Dallas Morning News, June 19, 1988
        - American Bar Association Journal, February 1987
        - Dallas Bar Headnotes Profile, 1988
        - American Board of Trial Advocates, Honor the Judiciary, November 1989
      - Reunions:
        - UT Law School, 50th Reunion, April 14-15, 2000
        - Legal Services of North Texas Annual Equal Justice Award Event, June 25, 2002
        - Law School Honor, April 17, 1999
        - “Barefoot Sanders Award,” Greater Dallas Crime Commission, November 1999
        - UT 50th Reunion, April 12, 2008
        - Reunion, 2004
        - SMU Dedication Ceremony, (pictures), January 2005
        - Murnane, Thomas G., NOHS Award Nomination Information
        - UT alumni Awards Dinner, March 20, 2002
        - UT 100 years celebration, April 6, 2002
        - NDHS Homecoming Parade, 2001
        - 50th Reunion (non-law school), April 6 – 7, 2000
        - Texas Cowboys Alumni Association
        - Class of 1949, University of Texas Reunion, Steering committee, 1999
        - UT Law School Reunions, 1990, 1995
        - USNSA Anthology Project, December 1997
        - UT Cheerleader Alumni
        - Kennedy Reunion, November 15, 1994
        - North Dallas High School Directory, 1995
        - Law School Honors, 1999
        - North Dallas High School Distinguished Alumnus, March 1995
  - 1972 Senate Campaign: (Box 2009-220/5)
    - Senate Campaign Supporter’s Numbers, 1972
    - Senate Campaign Supporters, 1972
    - Calendars, 1970-1972
    - Barefoot’s Tower Cards
  - Calendar, 1963
  - Calendar, 1969
  - Senate Campaign, 1972 (Box 2010-009/1)
    - Out-of-State Campaign Contributions correspondence
    - Polls
    - Press Releases (by date of release)
    - Press Releases (by subject matter
    - Questionnaires
    - Scheduling
    - Tower, John information about
      - Tower
      - Significant absences
      - Record
    - Vote Registration
    - County Lists
    - Washington D.C. correspondence
  - Senate Campaign, 1972 (Box 2010-009/5)
    - State Headquarters Mailing Lists
      - Bentsen Managers
      - County and District Clerks
      - Dallas County Precinct Chairman
      - Environmentalists
      - Fairmont Luncheon
      - Miscellaneous
      - State Democratic Executive Committee (SDEC) contacts
      - State Convention Delegates and Alternates
      - Teachers
      - Texas Motor Transport Association
      - University of Texas (UT) Law Graduates, 1949-1951
      - Young Democrats
      - Youth
    - Media
      - Media Buys
      - Newspapers
      - Television Stations
    - Mexican-American Affairs
      - Advance man, etc.
      - Campaign manual
      - Manager mailings
      - Personnel
      - Rental Agreement
      - Strategy meetings
  - Senate Campaign, 1972 (Box 2010-009/5)
    - Itinerary #2
    - Itineraries - General election
    - Bentsen Mailing list
    - Barefoot-Personal
    - Campaign Materials
      - Other races, Yarborough manual
      - Ad copy - Spots
      - Barefoot's positions
      - Sanders biographies
    - Election results
      - Primary and runoff
      - November 7
      - Tower-Bush analysis
    - Financial reports
      - Federal
      - State
    - Invoices
    - Itinerary-Pre-primary
    - Mailing lists
      - Johnson, Lyndon B.1964
      - Labor
      - Agriculture
  - Campaign Contributors correspondence, 1972 (Box 2009-359/3)
    - By county (Texas)
      - Anderson-Zavala
    - Washington D.C.
    - Miscellaneous out-of-state
    - Pre-primary contributions
  - Dallas County campaign, 1972
  - Campaign correspondence by county, 1972 (Box 2009-359/1)
    - Anderson-Dallas #3
    - Dallas #4-Gregg (Box 2010-009/3)
    - Grimes-Lampasas (Box 2009-359/5)
    - La Salle-San Jacinto (Box 2009-359/2)
    - San Patrico-Zavala (Box 2010-009/4)
  - North Dallas High School, Debate Team, 1940-1942 (Box 2009-295/1)
  - Military:
    - “The Mercer Cluster,”, 1944
    - Navy Record and I.D., 1940s
  - University of Texas:
    - Annual Roundup Rodeo, 1947
    - Rodeo Photographs, 1940s
    - Photographs and Ephemera, 1940s and undated
    - Central America
  - Dallas 1950s:
    - Award of Merit Application, 1951
    - Personal, 1950s
  - Texas Congress, 1952-1959:
    - Scrapbook – Clippings – Texas Congress, 1950s
    - Campaign Speeches and Radio, 1952
    - Texas Legislative Directories, 1950s
    - Clippings and Printed Material, 1950s
    - Texas Legislature, 1952-1957
  - U.S. Attorney:
    - Clippings, Printed Material, and Ephemera, 1960s
    - Personal, October-December 1963
    - Personal, April 1-June 30, 1963
    - Personal, January-March 1963
  - Printed Material, 1970s-1960s
  - Political Pre-Judgeship Material, 1950s-1970s
  - 1972 Senate Campaign:
    - Clippings from George Christian, 1972
    - Political Pre-Judgeship Clippings, 1970s
    - Political Pre-Judgeship Clippings, 1972 (Box 2009-295/2)
    - Barefoot’s Press Releases
    - Press Release Pool, 1972
    - Barefoot Press II
    - Run-off Releases
    - Duplicate Clippings
    - Campaign Materials, 1972
    - Clippings, Photocopies, 1972
    - Clippings, 1972
  - Federal Judgeship:
    - News clippings – Judgeship, 1979-2006
    - Judgeship Material, 1980s-1990s
    - Judgeship, 1979-2006
    - Historic Dem. 06
    - Oral History – (Dallas Public Library), Draft 1984
    - Judicial, 1979 -2006
    - Judge – Poems – Clerks
    - Correspondence, 1990s
    - Judgeship, photos, 1990s
    - Judgeship, 1990s
    - Texas Exes Membership, 1994
    - November 6 Luncheon, Judges list plus Clerks
  - Political files, 1961-1978 (Box 2010-092/1)
    - Political correspondence, 1975
    - Political correspondence, 1976
    - Political correspondence, 1977
    - Gary Weber for Mayor contributions, 1976
    - Election Analyses, 1976
    - John Tower info (empty)
    - Bob Krueger info, 1977
    - Press clippings, 1977
    - Energy-President's program, 1977
    - Ralph Yarborough's record (including financial disclosure, 1972
    - Congratulatory letters, 1965
    - Personal file-Corresondence, 1961-1964
    - Travel around state prior to 1978 campaign
      - Collin-McKinney
      - Tarrant-Fort Worth
      - Gregg County-Longview
      - Waco
      - John Hannah-East Texas
      - Valley (Harlingen, McAllen, Raymondville, etc.
      - Houston
      - Nueces County and Area
      - Sherman-Denison
      - Austin
      - Denton
      - San Antonio
      - Midland-Odessa
      - El Paso
      - Wichita Falls
      - Amarillo
      - Lubbock
      - Beaumont
      - Travel
  - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Bpx 2010-009/6)
    - Dallas County, re: Congressional campaign, 1958
    - Sanders' Personal, 1959
    - Thank you letters and congratulations, 1958
    - Miscellaneous campaign, 1958
    - Truman Diamond Jubilee, 1959
    - Correspondence, 1958
    - Miscellaneous, 1960
    - Texas Mental Health Code, 1957
    - Sanders' Personal correspondence, 1957
    - Sanders' Personal correspondence, 1966
  - Correspondence, 1957-1964 (Box 2010-009/2)
    - Dallas Grand Jury, 1962
    - Southern Methodist University (SMU) Seminar, 1962
    - Vice President's visit, 1963
    - Federal Grand Jury-Lubbock, 1963
    - Federal Grand Jury-Wichita Falls, 1963
    - Sanders' Personal, October 1961-January 1962
    - Texas Bar Joural-Civil Rights Article, 1964
    - Briefs, 1961-1962
    - Correspondence with Senator Ralph Yarborough, 1963
    - Summary Witness-Criminal Tax Trial-Testimony by Joe Houston
    - Federal Grand Jury-Amarillo, 1963
    - Lists-Personal, 1962, 1964
    - Luncheon Lists, 1963
    - Class Cocktail Party-Bar Convention, 1963
    - Archibald Cox Reception, 1963
    - 1950-1986, 2000 (Box 2009-359/6)
    - Miscellaneous material
    - Christmas cards
    - Letters from VIPs
  - Article on name "Barefoot"
  - Photographs
    - US Attorney
    - 1960
    - 1963
    - 1964-1970
    - 1970
    - Law Clerks
    - Lyndon B. Johnson photos
    - Lyndon B. Johnson oversized photo (Box 3S182)
    - 1940-1950 (Box 2009-359/6)
    - 1950-1960
    - 1970-1980
    - 1980-2000
    - 2000
    - Campaign/Congress, 1958
    - Campaign, 1960
    - Campaign/Senate1972
    - Judicial
    - Portrait photo of Sanders
    - Attorney General's visit, 1961
    - Sanders' Personal-Industrial Investments, 1962
    - Rambler Road Roofing Repairs, 1963
    - Sale of Newcombe Property, 1963
    - Speech file, 1961-1962
    - Congratulatory mail-Judgeship, Vol. II 1968
    - Sanders' Personal, 1961
    - Sanders' Personal-Oil Venture (Schneider and Murray Well), 1963
    - Sanders' Personal, July-September 1963
    - Speech file, 1963
    - Sanders' Personal, 1957
  - Card catalogs of various individuals throughout Texas related to Sanders' career and campaigns. There is also a photograph of a WWII Destroyer, possibly the one Sanders served on. (Box 2010-009/7-8)
  - [Stored on-site at SRH]
  - Oversize Materials: (Box 2AA13)
    - Clippings – “Bare Facts” and Mercer University, 1944
    - Oversize photos, 1940s, 1970s, 1990s
    - Clippings, 1950s
    - University of Texas Diploma and Seal, 1949
    - Clippings, 1940s
    - U.S. Congressional campaign, scrapbook pages, 1958
    - U.S. Congressional campaign, 1958
    - Clippings, Kennedy-Johnson Campaign, 1960 (Box 2AA14)
    - Sketch, U.S. attorney, 1960s
    - Clippings, U.S. attorney, 1960s
    - Clippings, Washington D.C., 1960s
    - Clippings, 1970s (Box 2AA15)
    - Clippings, Senate Campaign, 1972
    - Federal Court Improvement Act, 1994 (Box 2AA16)
    - Obituaries, 2008
    - Clippings on Appointment, 1978-1979
    - Clippings, non-case related
    - Clippings, DISD de-segregation Case, 1981-2005
    - Clippings, Hunt, R.A.J. Cases
    - Clippings on Cases
    - U.S. Senate Campaign Posters, 1972 (Box OD1316)